Don't write towards irony. Don't write
towards like snark or loftiness. Write
towards compassion, you know, write
towards real. Right towards the real.
>> It's like anything that you master in
life. The point of mastery isn't
virtuosity. The point of mastery is
there comes a time when you don't have
to try as hard anymore.
Welcome friends. In this episode of
Insights at the Edge, my guests are
Annie Lamont and her personal husband
Neil Allen. We're talking about their
new book, Good Writing: 36 Ways to
Improve Your Sentences. Neil Allen is a
writer, a spiritual coach and speaker.
He's a former journalist and corporate
executive, self-described hack writer,
someone who can write on Q on deadline.
He's the author of Shapes of Truth and
Better Days. Annie Lamont. Maybe you've
heard of her. Maybe you've read one of
her books.
She's the author of 20 books, including
seven novels, non-fiction work, and
beloved best-selling collections of
autobiographical essays, including
Traveling Mercy's, Plan B, and Grace
Eventually.
I think of both of you as members of my
soul family. from my heart to yours and
now including all of our listeners.
Welcome.
>> Well, thanks Tammy. We feel exactly the
same way. You're you're a really beloved
cousin.
>> We love this community, too.
>> We do.
>> Good writing. Neil, you created this
collection of rules for improving your
sentences. Tell me a bit about the
origin.
>> Yeah, the origin is so these are rules
um that I started to pick up when I was
a journalist. And so the assumption in
these rules is that you've got a
grammatical sentence. How do you make
that sentence better in the sense of
being being able to better persuade the
reader to read the next sentence that
follows and the next sentence that
follows? And the difference between
somebody who looks at themselves
fundamentally as a writer and somebody
who looks at themselves as a subject
matter expert who writes is that the
writer is actually more interested in
the sentence than the content. So um to
be interested in the sentence means to
notice that it has a lot of
possibilities after it's grammatical.
And I I started picking the first rule I
picked up from an a really uh helpful
editor was write with your verbs, right?
If you use a vivid verb instead of a
dull verb, if you use trudged instead of
walking, you pull the reader in better.
And that was my start and that was very
useful. And then I started to collect
other rules, you know, question
transitions, prefer Anglo-Saxon brutal
short words over Latin8 long complicated
words. And eventually I noticed I had,
you know, first four or five and then
eight or 10. And a few years ago I
noticed I had gotten more than a few
years ago, maybe 10 or 15 years ago, I
noticed I had gotten up to about 30 or
so such such rules.
And uh one day I looked around and
looked for who else has rules. Maybe I
can add to these, you know, and I was
kind of astonished because a lot of
writers had lists of these kind of rules
on how to improve a sentence, how to
make it better. And but they were
um Hemingway had four rules and Elmore
Leonard had eight and Margaret Atwood
has 10. the the most that I saw out
there was uh Martin Amos had 15, right?
And I was like, but they're more than
that. And then I looked around, is there
a book that collects them? And that's
how books get written is you see that
that book isn't already out there and
it's tug and it tug and it tugged at me.
And so my interest in writing the book
was to write a book that hadn't been
written before. And then my interest
when writing the book was, as it is for
um a lot of us,
the fun of writing one sentence after
another. So Annie and I look at each
other more or less as people who make
sentences. And this I just thought this
book isn't out there. Let's see what
whether we can get it out there.
I noticed as I was reading Good Writing,
I was like, I don't think I can ever
write another sentence as long as I live
after writing this book. I'm all in a
knot. I don't even know if I can speak a
sentence. But then as I got to the
conclusion and Annie, you wrote about
this notion of having three drafts
>> and I I felt liberated to use these
tools. So I wonder if you can explain
that idea of the three drafts. Well, you
know, I I wrote a whole book about it,
bird by bird, that basically, I think,
encourages people because none of the
writers they love write good first
drafts. No one knows what they're doing
until they finished a first draft.
Really, I can't think of it. Muriel
Spark, the great English World War II
writer, felt that she had headset,
dictapone headsets on and was taking
dictation from God. But that I mean
first of all that's such a very angry
thing to say and aggressive but um like
if that was true why would you say it to
other writers but most of us write
really god-awful first drafts. Neil
really doesn't because he was a
journalist for 15 years. He wrote
because he's always under deadline right
but um the rest of us uh write a really
terrible first draft. I said in the in
bird by bird that it was the uh child's
draft. you just get it all down and it's
way too long and the pros is too purple
and you use overly long descriptions and
whatnot. And then the second draft is
the grown-up's draft and you go through,
it's like Dr. Spock, the pediatrician
said to mothers with two-year-olds, you
must be firm and friendly. and you go
through and you're firm and friendly and
you say this really doesn't go there and
let's save it for somewhere else which
means you're not you know it's getting
cut and you go through and you really
and the second draft is really fun.
That's sort of what you're in it for is
that you take something that was 10,000
words and you bring it down to the 5,000
that it will really um end up being. And
then the third draft is a dental draft.
You sort of go tooth by tooth and you
that's paragraph by paragraph or passage
by passage or sentence by sentence. You
wiggle them and jiggle them and you poke
them and you see if anything needs help.
Sometimes they're just fine and healthy.
Other times they need a cleaning. other
times they need, you know, and you and
and so there's a really systematic way
to go from this rush of ideas or visions
or memories or
I just a
idea for a novel or a screenplay or a
memoir that comes out pouring out to it
being something really tight without
losing its your voice or its juiciness
or whatever.
But I think that's what gives writers
hope is that none of us know what we're
doing until we finish the first draft.
And then the second draft is really fun.
>> And that's really where these rules of
writing for most people come in in terms
of their application is the second draft
and the dental draft.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. We say that we say this is a book
about second drafts. Bird by Bird is
about a book about how do I
>> why
>> how do I make myself a writer and get
into the first draft and this is really
a second draft book
>> much more technical than bird by bird.
Bird bra bird is much more uh fluidly
about a process and this is this and
because it's technical my problem was I
didn't want to write a technical man
manual like a grimarian might you know
which makes it sound like everything's
right and wrong and these are these
rules can be broken and you can you can
argue with them and they are not right
and wrong they are rhetoric and
persuasion
>> and everybody's got a different way of
using persuasion. And so I didn't run a
I didn't feel like that kind of expert.
I felt like they were useful to me. And
so I tried to write just what came top
of my head about my experience with
using these as more or less a users
manual rather than a technical manual
maybe.
>> Now you shared these rules with Annie
towards the beginning of your time
together dating. What was your response,
Annie, when you when you looked at this?
>> I think I think he shared them with me
on our fourth or fifth date. So, this is
10 years ago. And I was amazed. I mean,
I thought they were great. Some of them
obviously I knew, but they were written
down in a way that had structure and
cons, it was concise and just brilliant.
And so, I started giving them out to all
of my students at my writing workshops
and whatnot. And then uh a couple of
years ago, Neil put them into a book and
um and did these meditations on them,
you know, and these little essays on
each rule with a lot of examples. Now,
Neil is we're just very different
stylistically. He's really organized
mentally and he can be professorial
and he has a lot of brilliant examples.
I mean, he'll bring up Socrates very
casually in a conversation about, you
know, Jean Benet Ramsay or something.
And then I'm more like the denmother for
the third graders. I bring in the
cupcakes and I say, "I really want you
to consider doing this. I think you can
do it. You're there's a lot of help
available. Your voice is important.
You're important." And so I looked at
his book and I loved it when I said,
"Hey, you know what? I know something
about writing, too." and um Mr. Man and
um and so I asked if I could contribute
my responses to his to his essays and my
ex my own examples. So that's how it all
came about. But so after all of a sudden
he had them posted at his website
shapesofruth.com
and I was just referring people to them.
I was saying just go to
shapesoftruth.com you'll find the rules
you know and people were just blown away
by them. That's how we both knew we were
on to something.
>> It turned out that that difference in
style
um really lucked out um because the way
Annie decided that she might uh horn in
on this book is
uh respond to each of my um essays. So,
it's a call in response where she always
gets the last word, which she likes a
lot, and in some cases she disagrees
with the rule and so she gets the last
word on the rule. Um, but it works with
our style because I'm an explainer and
my greatest fault in writing is I
overexlain, right? And so, I'm going to
I'm that's just what I do. I I kind of
look at things and kind of try to put
them together and find patterns and
explain why the pattern works and that
sort of thing. And Annie's cathartic,
right? She connects in a different way
to with the reader so that the reader
can and the way it works in the book is
that and it was just serendipity that by
my going first, her going second, you
get the rule, you get an explanation of
the rule, and then you get kind of a
coach helping you uh feel comfortable
with the rule.
>> And and the dead mother who says, "Go
ahead, break the rule."
>> Plus, you get to end on on on humor
because she's much funnier than I am.
>> And also I have a very strong uh
spiritual interest in people writing
because I feel and and it's all all
through good writing. The my feeling
that if you want to write and you don't
get around to it, it's just going to
plague you. It's going to hurt you at
the end of your life that you had you
wanted to get your memories down for
both for your grandchildren and just for
your own self. and you wanted to tell
this novel that you started in college,
but that life interfered and you had a
family and you had a job and now you're
65 and and the Neil's inner critic is
telling you you it's too late to start
or there's or there's no way that you
could da da da da da and and so my
spiritual influence I think is to say
this is really about your heart and your
soul that you find a way to get a little
bit of work done every day and these
These are some of the hacks we use to do
get our own work done.
You you mentioned that you're both very
different kinds of writers and that's
displayed in the book clearly and one of
the things you talk about is how in
finding our own voice you write Neil
like music
writing relies on the integration of
melody rhythm and harmony and that we're
adept at all three but usually one is
prominent and that's your default talent
or writing style and I wonder if you can
explain that more and then take us into
the Beatles as writers and where you and
Annie fit into that.
>> Yeah, that's funny. I I uh so you know I
I have a spiritual practice that came up
through diamond heart and it's got a lot
of georgieian fourth uh way um uh
content including this idea that we are
three- centered beings head body heart
right head body chest however you want
to put it and they correspond in music
with melody is the head center that
curiosity the bright stuff, the the
pulling stuff and making leaps of faith
and leaps of interest. And then um
rhythm is the body center wanting to
dance. And heart is the harmony that
music requires, right? Of being
relational and adding voices and getting
them to blend and that sort of thing.
And writing is the exact same way,
right? I I get my ideas like ideas
always start with curiosity and they
come in through the head center and then
I move them through my body where they
can kind of coalesce into patterns right
dance patterns which aren't unlike
chemical veilances and they either work
or they don't to the ear and then when
I've when I've succeeded in those two
then I still have the reader to be
connecting with and that's the harmony
and I connect with the reader by
bringing in the familiar and balancing
it with the unfamiliar and kind of
tugging them along and patting them and
and being bringing cupcakes, that sort
of thing. And I thought about and
writeed write about this how you can
really kind of see that in music in the
Beatles where you know there probably is
no better melodist in our generation or
several generations than Paul McCartney.
He is a pure melodist leaping intervals.
He just thinks up. You you watch that
that um the making of the of the Let It
Be and you just watch him invent a
melody and it turns into a song in I
think 18 minutes. They've got it
complete, right? But he's just got these
melodies going. And then you listen to
John and John has a very very narrow
first one thing, Paul has a four octave
had a five octave range voice. And so
those leaping intervals work for his
voice, too. But John has more like a
three octave and he doesn't think in
melody, right? John thinks in rhythm.
John um Ringo might be right when Ringo
says John is the greatest rhythm
guitarist who ever lived and Ringo
doesn't have to and Paul don't have to
keep the beat in the Beatles. It's a
very strange thing because John keeps
the beat and John's also the leader
more or less of the group and so they
follow his rhythm and he stretches notes
and he and he and Ringo can follow him
just locked up. They're they're
absolutely in love with the rhythm and
the beat. And then interestingly, Ringo
is
um a rhythmic melodist. His his
instrument is the drums, but Ringo's
trick in being a drummer is he's never
following the bass player, right? In
jazz, everybody follows the beat of the
bass player, including the drummer,
right? You think the drummer is keeping
the beat. No, the bass player is keeping
the beat. And in rock and roll, there's
a lot of that, too. often the drummer
keeps beat. Ringo's following the voice.
He's following the melody all the time.
All he's listening to, he's interacting
kind of intuitively with John on the
rhythm, but he's listening to whoever's
singing the song. And then George is
kind of a harmonic rhythmic guy. He also
isn't a he's an okay melodist. I mean
something is beautiful beautiful melody
but he's thinking first of harmony
because that's who he is you know he is
this spiritual harmonist and so you can
find your own beetle and the point to
that is to notice what's my strength and
if my strength is like I'm a rhythmic
writer um fundamentally rhythmic writer
I I I don't worry about I don't have to
read my sentences aloud to myself
because I know I'm that's what I've
captured in my lifetime in my voice is
the ability to feel at ease creating the
rhythms of and these aren't the rhythms
of amic pentameter these are the rhythms
of conversation and so I can be
conversationally rhythmic in my writing
um Annie's a an incredible melodist I
could never come up with the kind of
metaphors and the kind of break points
and the kind of leaps that Annie comes
up with so I build on my strengths and I
and I struggle and occasionally bring in
a metaphor. Annie can just drop one
metaphor after another after another.
>> What is the value of knowing which type
of musical writer you are?
>> So you don't get hung up on trying to be
something you aren't, right? I'm not
going to get hung up. John was okay with
not being as good a melodist as Paul. it
didn't stop him from producing music
that we all listen to just as much.
>> You know, it's just very important to
know what um what you're good at and
what you love to do with writing. Like
with a couple years ago, the Washington
Post asked me to write some pieces on um
getting older. I wrote a series of 12
over the course of a year and back when
the Post was still the Post. And um but
what when they came to me they had this
idea that I would write it would be much
more sociological. You know I would talk
to other people across all different
socioeconomic
um levels and and I said I don't do
that. That's not what I'm good at. I I
don't want and I also don't want to. But
I can write about what it's like for me
and what it's like for my friends who
have gotten so much older and um and so
they went for that. But it's I know that
I'm not going to ever write like Neil.
I'm not going to ever write like
Isabella Yende. I'm not going to write
like Barbara Kings. And it causes me
pain that I will never write like
Barbara Kings or George Saunders. I hate
that. It makes me feel there's no point.
But I can write like me, you know, and I
can tell my stories and I can tell my
stories in my voice and that's the m
that's the only music I can play. And
also it's like John Prime, you know,
John Prime was not Eric Clapton or vice
versa. I much prefer John Prime, but um
you find out what you love and what
comes naturally to you and what you want
to do as a writer and you you stick to
that. You don't stick to that, but then
u like I know Neil thinks I'm Paul
McCartney, but he's actually my last my
least favorite beetle. Plus, as I
mentioned in Good Writing, we went to
the Oakland Coliseum to hear him and I
we caught COVID. So, then I completely
turned on him. But I, you know, I love
John. I love I love the other three of
them. And I'm very I'm happy or at least
in old age, I'm accepting of the fact
that I can tell my stories the way I
tell my stories. There are a lot of
tangents, you know, and and um Neil
doesn't isn't as tangential as I do.
Neil is an explainer. He will explain,
you know, till the cows come home. But I
will be going off on all these tangents
and and then I can somehow because I
have a gift bring it all together and
help bring you back home. That's what I
can do. And I can't do other things. And
um and so I we wanted writers to know
that their natural voice and the stuff
that they love both about life and
living and their own lives is theirs
uniquely to tell. And that's what we
want to hear. That's the song we want to
hear.
>> Yeah. Once I found my natural voice,
it's like anything that you master in
life. The point of mastery isn't
virtuosity. The point of mastery is
there comes a time when you don't have
to try as hard anymore. And once you can
just sort of sit back and ease into it
and let it flow on its own, then you can
use your mastery not to get better at
your mastery, but to use it as a groove
in which you can center your view of the
outside world. And the the the the
uh the metaphor I use for this or
analogy I use for this is that a good
river guide um knows the river so well
that you barely see him or her working
the paddle. And if you watch him or her,
they're not even bothering to watch the
currents anymore because they know the
river anymore. What are they watching?
The otter playing on the banks. Nothing
to do with their mastery. And so when I
found my voice and accepted it that I
wasn't going to be William Faulner ever
and and and took my voice and decided to
work with it whatever it was and
strengthen it whatever it was to the
point that I could uh feel comfortable
with it at any time. Uh then I got to
use writing to write about anything I
wanted to and it became a channel to
explore the world.
I like to essentialize. So, I'm going to
pull out a quote from good writing that
I thought very essentialized. All of the
rules, these rules economize,
favor the plain spoken and specific,
keep the reader attention sharp, and in
other ways, show respect for the
audience's time and desire for novelty.
Neil, you wrote this and I thought we
could go through it a bit and it would
be a way that you could point out some
of the rules that support each one of
these essential principles. So, firstly,
these rules economize I I love this. I
you know, I'm just sitting here. I'm
writing a long text to somebody as I'm
reading the book yesterday and I
thought, "Wow, that's really long,
Tammy. I'm apologizing for something and
I have a lot to say in my apology and
I'm like the last thing this person
wants to read is a text this long. So
then I thought I'm going to use the
rules and I went back and I probably
took 30% out and I thought this is
awesome. So go ahead talk a little about
economizing.
>> So interestingly by the way you say I
wrote that sentence that's my favorite
sentence in the book and I have it. It
is and I have a complete absence of
sense of owning it. I don't know. It's
the sort of thing that just comes and so
I really can sort of see the
interdependence of the world and see
that I didn't write this book. My
parents wrote it. My friends wrote it.
All the things that influence and got
channeled into it. But that sentence in
particular, I didn't write that
sentence. Now that you you read it aloud
to me, I notice that the the answer to
your question is the end of the
sentence, right? So the end of the
sentence says something about respect
the reader attention and desire for
novelty
uh attention span it could say right
I've forgotten the exact words you read
but um that's exactly it
>> the audience's time which is also what
we're doing here I want to respect our
listeners time and their desire to hear
something new that's going to help them
but keep going Neil
>> no that's it I've economized I answered
your question it's time and respect for
novelty People want novelty and people
want to be able to conclude it so they
can do something new and they want that
in.
>> We're going to go into it a little bit
more. We're going to go into it a little
bit more. What are some of the top ways
you both know when you go back into
draft number two and three? Andy, I'm
going to economize. What do you like?
This is it. This is what I do.
>> Well, Neil and I show each other
everything we write before we submit it
to an agent or an editor. And so I will
um ask him I will know something is 500
words too long and I will ask him to go
through because you know by the time
you've written the draft your eye starts
glancing off stuff you know that you
really would
might have paid better attention to or
cut or um or shortened and ne it's so
great to have somebody go through and
say this goes on too long this desri you
don't want this long a description you
know you wrote too on paragraphs about
your the trip to the local dump with
your father when you were eight years
old and I would love one short paragraph
do it again it's just about put you know
when I was coming up same with Neil
there was this phrase you about putting
it through the typewriter again and it
meant through you you went through the
whole draft and you you looked at every
paragraph and you took out everything
you could or like Jessica Mittford's
great paraphrase that you must kill your
little darlings that You go through and
there are these sentences you shoehorned
in that uh that are supposed to make the
reader think you're smarter or more
educated or more ironic or less of a
buzzkill than you really are. And you
just love it so so so much and you just
have to take it out if it's one of your
darlings because it's going to stick out
to the reader. I um I'm the same with
you. When I write a text, it's way too
long, you know, and I'll go through and
I'll cut it in half. I mean, every
second draft I write, I've cut out a
quarter of the first draft because the
the length of the first the stuff got me
to uh to to to having so um the choice
the ability to select the stuff that
really shines, the stuff that is uh
really resonant or that is um
descriptive. All of us write
descriptions that are way too long and
we maybe we write the description
beautifully and it's like that's nice
but being a writer means I got to get
you to the next page and I am not going
to read three paragraphs about your uh
kindergarten class you know I will read
one I will read one if you wrote it
carefully really happily because I will
identify it'll be a mirror for me so um
everything I write is too long every
draft every email every everything. And
um one thing this book often talks about
um trusting your editors because editors
will very gently say, "This goes on too
long. You're losing me." And um
>> it's summed up in rule 14, remove the
boring stuff.
>> Yeah. Remove the boring stuff. And and
for me, and I think for most people,
most of the boring stuff is I've got to
prove what I just said.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I've got to explain it and prove it.
And we get taught in high school and
college that that's the model. If you
say something, prove it and show your
work, show your explanation, right?
Well, that's that's not in real life.
People trust each other or distrust each
other. And they make a snap judgment.
And if they distrust you, maybe they
need to see some proof. But if they
trust what you're writing and they're a
friendly reader, you don't have to prove
what you said. And usually they kind of
can fill in gaps and get it on their own
and want to move on much faster than I
think they do. Annie's much better at
removing the boring stuff. She doesn't
even put it in her first round. I have I
have to cut so much more.
Okay, we covered
these rules. Economize favor the plain
spoken and specific. This notion of the
plain spoken. Don't be a showoff. I
really liked that part of the rules. I
thought yes I there's so little plain
spoken and modest and true in the
popular culture that when we come upon a
writer or a person who you know says
what they mean mean what they say mean
what they say and don't say it mean my
heart leaps because there's something so
um comforting about people not showing
off about people not doing literary
pyrochnics One of the rule is rules,
Neil's rules is if it sounds literary,
it isn't. You know, you got to take it
out. It's a it's um pretentious or it's
elitist or it's just showing off. So,
you'll think that we're fancier writers
than we are. I don't want to read fancy
writers. I want to read someone. There's
a great quote in there by the wonderful
screenwriter of Miss Del Mrs. Delire,
Randy May Singer, who said, "Tell me a
story, make me care." And when someone
will tell me a story in plain spoken
English where they're focusing on who
the character is and and helping me get
grounded in the setting and helping the
plot move along. Oh, I'm so grateful.
I'm so grateful. And there is so little
of it. Everybody's told to make it
fancier, to burnish it, to make it
bounce off the page, to make it pop. You
know, I don't want that. I want you to
tell me a story and make me care.
This was your father had a neat way of
talking about it with nickel words. What
was it?
>> Yeah. Yeah. He taught me, you know, um
just that you could use nickel words to
describe things instead of these 25 cent
words that maybe you got from the
thesaurus. Now, we're big fans of the
thesaurus to help you find the right
word, to help you find the strongest
verb, which is, I think, rule one. But
by the same token, an um somebody using
a nickel word so that I don't have to
look it up means I'm going to keep
turning the page. It's interesting that
you brought up the thesaurus because
I've been one of those people when I see
people where they're in meetings or
something like that, then they pull up
the thesaurus and I'm like, "Oh god,
you're never going to really be able to
come up with something that has that
original a word that you both use,
quirky thing if you're using it the
source. it's going to feel sort of
forced and put on afterwards. So, when I
read that you both are fans of using a
thesaurus, you go so far as to call it a
book of magic spells, I thought, "Wow,
Tammy, once again, you're going to have
to open up your, you know, judgmental
ways."
>> And I tell the story of an old um a a an
old friend of mine who I was looking at
a she, it was back in the day of writing
by hand. And this was in sometime in the
probably late 70s, early 80s. And I she
was writing short stories at the time.
And I looked at a manuscript on her desk
and I saw all these piled up on every
once in a while there would be a word
with a whole bunch of other words piled
up on top of it. And I asked what that
was about and she said, "Oh, oh, that
word really stuck out to me. It might be
the right word. It's a really important
word for the for the story and I want to
make sure I get the exact right word and
so I'm adding in other ones that might
replace it. And that taught me that
that's what a thesaurus is. There is a
word that is perfect for what you are
trying to say. Go find it. And if I see
and you know you develop an ear over
time and that's not the right word. our
the most frequent conversation that
Annie and I have about
uh um writing while one of us is writing
a piece is what's the word for or what's
another word for blank. Yeah.
>> And and it's it's it is in the
thesaurus.
>> It isn't it isn't supposed to be in my
head. I'm not Shakespeare. I don't have
that many words in my head. Right. So, I
go to a thesaurus and find the perfect
work.
>> Okay. Keep the reader turning the page.
Keep them moving. Don't lose them. Don't
try to show off. And so, in the
beginning of our conversation, Neil,
when you were talking about these rules,
you talked about
>> using Anglo-Saxon words and not Latinate
words. And Annie jokingly in the book in
your commentary on this, you write about
how you were a college dropout at age 19
and you had to look up what this even
meant. And I I had to look it up, too. I
was like, what are we talking about? And
so I believe in being a listener
advocate, which is like being a reader
advocate. One of the things you write
about uh in in better writing is an
antagonistic reader uh is someone who's
confused by by what's happening. And I
thought an antagonistic listener to any
conversation also is someone who feels
confused. I don't want our listeners to
feel confused. I advocate for them. So I
want to go back, Neil, to this. The
Anglo-Saxon words, Latinate words. What
are you talking about?
>> Okay. So you're ignoring my uh subhead
to that um chapter. Certainly rule six
is prefer Anglo-Saxon words. It's a
short way of putting what I'm saying.
And then I explain it. favor shorter,
punchier Anglo-Saxon words over fancy
abstract Latinate words. Now, what I
explain in in here, and that's why I
these are kind of meditations in a
certain way, Annie puts that fancy word
on them. What I explain is that and you
pick up this kind of new little piece of
knowledge if you hadn't been taught it
before by reading this book that
actually English is has two streams
coming into it. Most languages come kind
of directly through one stream. you
know, Hindi comes out of Sanskrit in a
kind of direct line and you can follow
it and and but weirdly because of the
way England developed um there's a
stream coming from the north which is a
bunch of Scandinavian and Germanic
languages that are called Anglo-Saxon
and there's a stream coming in from the
south which are all the Italian,
Spanish, um uh French cognates that sit
inside of English and it's a handy if
you start to notice that you start to
notice that a whole lot of the
multi-elabic boring words are coming up
from the south and a whole lot of the
crisp brutal get you right into the
scene words are coming in from the
north.
You talked, Annie, about how refreshing
it is when someone says what they mean,
means what they say, says it directly,
and I notice I I also find that
extraordinarily refreshing. So maybe
it's my love of the Anglo-Saxon
directness that I didn't even know how
to call it that. But one of the things I
ask myself, and I'm curious what you
think about this, when I'm writing, is
if it's not quite coming across, it's
like I have to go more into my heart or
using your three- centered uh model,
Neil, more into my belly, like I have to
get deeper into the blood and bone and
the truth of what I'm trying to say. And
I wonder how that fits in with being
simple and direct and saying what we
mean really.
>> Well, I love that question. Um, I
mentioned in this book, as I've
mentioned in Bird by Bird, that
wonderful line of Shirley Jackson's that
a confused reader is an antagonistic
reader. And um, and I love being able to
follow along with the the musician who
is um, spinning this story and this
song. And um
I am
often
reminded of something I wrote 35 or
whatever years it was ago in Bird by
Bird where as a younger writer, I
thought I should write more in in a more
impressive way and I should write in a
way that really made me look more
educated and more New York and more
male, right? all those male East Coast
writers that I came up on, the you know,
John Updike and all the John's and uh
all the uh all the most famous writers
and all the New Yorker writers who were
mostly new east coast men, white men.
And I wrote in Bird by Bird like don't
write towards irony, don't write towards
like snark or loftiness. Write towards
compassion, you know, write towards
real. right towards the real. You know,
the ancient Greeks called God the really
real. And when someone is telling me,
whether it's a student or a writer, a
published writer is telling me a story
that is from the heart and that's really
real, it nourishes me. Oh, I'm so
starved for it and I'm so grateful for
it. And so I try to do that. And
sometimes I will be trying to uh because
Neil is so literate, not literary, but
he's just so intellectual that knowing
that he's going to read something I've
written, I might try to fancy it up a
little bit and to sound a little tiny
bit more like him. And then I'll go,
that's not my I can't sing my song in
Neil's voice, you know, PE. And so I'll
just draw myself back right from the
heart, right towards compassion, right
towards the really real. And um and it
just keeps being my way. And um
and I love come and I always tell my
writing students, write what you'd love
to come upon. And what I love to come
upon is is what we've been talking
about, you know, the compassionate, the
heartful instead of the the polished
mind, you know, the prism of the mind
writing. Also, a lot of these books, you
know, uh we found out something very
kind of shocking last year, which is
that 80% of all books in America are
bought a on iPhones and b at Amazon. And
so, if somebody is a Isn't that
shocking? I mean, that is
>> I didn't know that.
>> Yeah, that's not the world we came up
in. But, um we're still about hardbacks
and paper and whatnot. But at any rate,
in going back to the rule, you got to
get people to turn the page. If I'm
picking up a book in a bookstore or
reading the sample at ebooks and it's
lofty and I can't quite track it, I'm
not going to pay whatever I'm going to
pay $14 or $27 for it. And somebody
starts to tell me a story in a
distinctly human voice. Um, I am so
charmed and I'm so grateful and I'm
going to keep going.
>> Fancification is kind of uh u a form of
hierarchy and
um the idea of being sophisticated and
hierarchical and superior all kind of
settled in with fancification
making things really fancy. I'm going to
show any kind of showing off, any kind
of um intellectualizing for the sake of
intellectualizing.
And you can't have judgment and empathy
at the same time. They just can't
coexist. And people aren't looking at
books. I don't mean empathy that they're
going to agree with me. I mean empathy
that a member of my species that I care
about is writing to me.
>> Now, turning the page, getting the
reader to keep going, keep going, keep
going. Don't abandon this book. Annie, I
have to ask you this question. Part of
what gets me to turn the pages when
you're writing. And part of what will
all kinds of things will attract me if
I'm going to laugh out loud.
>> If I'm if something if someone can get
me to laugh out loud, that's, you know,
oh my god, the jackpot. You
>> reliably get me to laugh out loud. And
I'd like to know, is there any kind of
rule or anything under that that you can
help us with? Cuz laughing out loud,
that is such a joy.
>> Oh, thank you. I know it's it's the
reason reason for being here at all is
that incredible miracle of laughing with
somebody. You know, I always say
laughter is carbonated holiness. And I
actually believe that that when you're
laughing with somebody, it's holy. It's
and and also it's the most therapeutic
thing we do. But I have to say that in
my writing, I put in a lot of stuff that
is attempting to be funny and I take it
out. I kill my little darlings. I'm
either using it to try to get you to
think that I'm not a depressive or I'm
trying to seduce you with it and I have
to take it out and I have to I leave in
the stuff that feels really genuine. It
feels like there's a funny way of
looking at this that you might not have
thought about before. And um but you
know, I got funny as a weapon against
bullies because I looked so different
when I was a little kid and a teenager.
And I um I weaponized it. But then I
also found that in telling my story, I
could um get people to really pay
attention if I was a little bit lighter
than um uh and infused it with funny
moments. Told the truth, but also
infused it with funny moments. And the
other thing is when I was um a young
writer, I lived for writers who could
make me laugh out loud. from PG
Woodhouse to uh you know Charles
Portoris to uh um
you know Lorie Colewin and to laugh out
loud one to to be reading something and
to all a sudden laugh and look up to me
that is what heaven is like right
>> so humor is always about the absurdity
of the difficulty of life right humor is
how we if you if you just complain
as a straight complaint and you do it
and most people complain all day long,
right? Most conversation is people
complaining to each other about how hard
things are and what's about to happen
and what just happened and it's like,
"Oh, we're suffering, suffering,
suffering." And that's most
conversation. Most gossip is complaining
about other people, all of that. Um, and
if you just do it as a complaint, it's
unacceptable. You're a whiner. You're a
complainer. But if you do it as humor,
it's 100% acceptable. If you watch like
Robin Williams, that brilliant,
magnificent 40 minutes at Lincoln
Center, right? He is just riffing wildly
through all the complaints of civilized
life and and turning the complaint into
humor which we for some reason we can
accept it through humor and we don't
accept it
>> through being presented straight ahead
to us. I get to be the straight man in
our relationship and I it Annie lightens
up my life all day long.
One of your recommendations to people is
to read their writing out loud, to
listen to it. Does it keep your
attention as you're reading out loud?
What's the rhythm like? And I thought
this would be a fun
>> thing to share with our listeners. Thing
is one of the words you wouldn't use in
writing. And if I were going back and
editing that sentence, I wouldn't say
thing. I would say I think a wonderful
section of the book that I would love to
have you share with our listeners is one
of my favorite rules, rule 33. Write the
hard stuff. Don't shy from the big
mysteries of life. And I wonder if you
can read us an excerpt from that section
of the book. Both of you.
>> By the way, you just did a brilliant bit
of editing. I had it. Don't shy away
from the big mysteries of life. And you
and you knew the word away was
completely unnecessary and you dropped
it.
>> Economized.
>> You economized.
>> Take out the little words.
>> Nothing is ineffable.
Make the effort. Write the material
whose articulation first stumps you. The
stuff that makes people tick until that
last talk.
Finding a way to evoke the ineffable is
related to Donald Murray's idea that
syntactic failure is a sign you're
trying to say something important. In
other words, if it's hard to write, it's
probably worth writing.
Isn't the whole point of writing to
figure out something you don't already
know? Most fiction and biography writers
discover aspects of their characters
along the way. In general non-fiction,
the author seeks motivations and causes
for events. The act of writing refineses
the author's notions and often opens new
possibilities.
I once heard the novelist Sirius
complain that her protagonists keep
getting killed off at the end of the
story. She wants to protect her
characters from themselves but can't.
In many traditions, God is expected to
be so ineffable that it's hubris, even
sin, to try to explain the concept. But
those same traditions fill libraries
with stacks of theology, the study of
God. Don't pretend that anything is off
limits to your consideration and
articulation.
You go where your characters go, inside
and out, in their metaphysical
meanderings and their hikes through the
woods. Often non-fiction writers believe
that they must wrap things up neatly and
maintain an objective stance that might
wobble if contaminated by subjectivity
or the great irrational.
Vickenstein said, "The limits of
language are the limits of my world."
Well,
my words include mystery and
supernatural,
and my syntax includes questions and
paradoxical statements.
When I worked in daily newspapers, I
could only ask a question that could be
answered in the next paragraph.
Magazine, blog, and bookw writers often
restrain themselves the same way. But
that's a shame. They have room and
therefore license to raise the stakes
even if it makes some of their readers
uncomfortable.
Here is novelist Joseé Saramago on
what's important about the hard stuff.
Inside us there is something that has no
name. That something is what we are.
And here's how you do it. If you're
Cormarmac McCarthy,
they were watching out there past men's
knowing where stars are drowning and
whales f their vast souls through the
black and seamless sea.
And
>> then here's me. Thank you for letting us
read. This is what we love is to um get
to share really exactly what this book
is about. Please, please, please, please
write the hard stuff. Write about life
and death and loss and hope and how on
earth you survived that child or injury
or marriage. Find a way to write about
people's underlying fears. Maybe
psychological but also mystical fear of
death, of legacy, of emptiness and
lovableness. Write about who you think
you are deep down past the persona and
curation and the stories you believe
about yourself because
you are probably similar to me and I
love it when someone holds up a mirror.
I love revelation.
We're a species that craves stories
about itself. Tell us our story through
your lens. Whether in fiction or
non-fiction, it really is all you have
to offer us. We are all going to die.
Hit the decks. How do we live fully,
boldly in the face of that? This is hard
to think and write about, but we want
you to. It is essential that you try.
We're here on the incarnational side of
things to discover the truth of who we
are. We're animal, human, divine. That
is hard stuff to capture, but that is
what I most long to read. Truth. your
truth, our truth. Try. This will not go
well. But don't give up. Write an
incredibly terrible first draft that
will be way too long and overroought and
sophomoreic. Then take out all the
boring parts and see what is left. Then
try again and see if you can make it
better. Go deeper. Talk to people about
what you are working on and see if their
input throws some lights on for you or
even provides phrases that will help you
capture what you are after in your next
draft. P.S. I've always said that if you
want to be a writer, you should get the
smartest, funniest friends, but it is
best if they are not writers, too,
because then they won't let you steal
all their great lines about these
profound matters.
and a good if not laugh out loud moment,
broad smile moment at the end of that.
>> That was rule number 33. And I want to
end our conversation with something
you've already mentioned, but I want to
say a little bit more about it, which is
rule 36. Worship talented editors.
Writing is collaborative and editors
save your skin. At the end of the book,
Good Writing, you have this toolkit of
all the rules. I printed it out for
myself so I could have it. I'm going to
keep this. It's an incredibly terrific
reference. And here we are referencing
number 36, the final rule, worship
talented editors. And I thought to
myself, you know, how do you know that
this person's really a talented editor?
And furthermore, get your hands off my
writing. Like I notice I have this thing
of like please you're you're ruining it.
H how both of you how do you know when
that's your ego speaking or and you just
need to let go? This person really knows
better than me. How do you make that
assessment?
>> Well, um I really really trust Neil with
my work. Um and I but I don't always go
along with what he says. It's my book.
It's my piece and whatnot. But I trust
him because he has um a great eye and he
loves my work and he really truly wants
to just help me get better and better.
Helps me want to present something
that's just burnished to its most
beautiful sheen. You know, I I I came up
through newspapers um and uh I was stuck
with editors and some were good and some
were bad. And so I had to figure out how
to deal with that and how to how to how
to kind of look into that. And I over
time I developed a rubric that editors
are going to insert things that I call
mistakes or errors or wrong-headed
thinking. They are going to do that in a
in the rush of a newspaper. This is
especially true. and I notice if I pay
attention and notice that they've made
two improvements
for everything that I don't like that
they've done, then I've really got
nothing to complain about. And if they
make three improvements,
I've got something to learn from that
editor. Three improvements for every
mistake. And somehow
that's enough. Uh that's as much as I
know about how I select whether
somebody's trustworthy as an editor.
>> Yeah. And um it's funny because in my
when I was coming up and an editor
whether it was at a magazine or one of
my early novels would u make suggestions
uh line edit they would call it going
line by line and and making suggestions
and and crossing things out. I I would
take it personally. It would sort of
hurt my feelings. And then
and then rather early on I discovered
the miracle that an editor was bringing
to the book which is that they were
making me come up with better words,
better descriptions. They were taking
out the excess which really f it's like
getting a really great haircut where
where it frames your face in a way that
extra hair doesn't. And I ever since
then, I mean this is 45 years ago since
I published more than that published um
my first book, Hard Laughter. Ever since
that I have felt a desperate gratitude
um for editors um and there are editors
who don't get me and who um have harshed
me and have tried to get me to sound
more like the writers they love and I
have had to compromise with them but I
know I don't want to work with them
again because life is just way too short
>> and and editors who are who are good
universally do the same thing that Annie
and I do with each Jazz's work, which is
you just have to through an entire adult
life, no matter how much uh you think
you've learned or you're advanced or
your psychology works for you or
whatever, you still have to do the
sandwich. You have to if you're going to
criticize something,
>> you've got to start with something
that's praise.
>> Yeah.
>> And then, and Annie and I do this, this
is brilliant.
>> Uh you've really got it. You've really
captured it. The structure is perfect. I
just have a few quibbles about some
things. And you'll notice it looks all
marked up, but it's all minor stuff,
Annie. Don't worry about it. And
>> and prepare them,
>> right? And first remind and then close
before I hand it to her. And I say, and
I just want to say the world needs this
or usually the word brilliant. Again,
the word brilliant is as I think I say
this in the book is as universally
useful as an editor as the word cute is
for shopping for clothes. Right?
>> In closing that one thing that writers
that writers who have not been published
perhaps or who have not been happily
published don't know is that you're not
you don't have to do it alone. You know,
the American way is that you should do
things alone and really not enjoy it and
that will indicate your commitment to
it. But the truth is that you need
someone to read your work for you. You
need a fresh set of eyes on it. You need
someone you trust who respects your work
and who is going to um help you get it
to be the best it can possibly be. You
don't and there will be many people
along the way who are going to step in
and help you. And I think that takes
away a great deal of fear. Whether it's
a writing partner, whether it's a
writing group at the local independent
bookstore. I mean, I started teaching
writing at Book Passage 30 some years,
35 years ago. Jack Sam was a little boy
on the floor with Legos and you know,
pretzels in a in a Ziploc bag. And um I
had people fi formed writing groups then
that are still together where two of the
five have gotten published. You don't
have to do it alone and it can be
something that you really love and that
enriches your life and is a dream come
true
in the description of the rule. I mean
the very first phrase here, writing is
collaborative. I mean I underlined that
because I thought oh no writing is the
one thing you do just by yourself. It's
the one thing you sit at, you know, but
what you're saying here is no, it's
actually collaborative. The question I
have about this is what makes you a good
collaborator, not the editor, but what
do you what's the inner work you have to
do
>> to be available for collaboration when
you're dealing with this expression that
you are so invested in? Yeah, you have
to have the the way I think about it is
I have to have an awareness that I have
blind spots
>> and that that's primarily the editor
that's the editor's first job is to make
up for my blind spots, right? And that
and that I can't know my blind spots.
Now, the first time I got a publishing
contract for a book, I bought the book
back because I couldn't trust the
editor. And that's because I want my
blind spots to be taken care of because
otherwise I'm going to have them
smacking in my face when people read the
book and say but but or why' you do
that? Right? And the editor, the editor
is my cheerleader. And the editor or an
agent, both of them kind of do this
thing where if I don't detect that they
love something about it and think this
thing needs to be out there in some way,
then they're not doing their job. So
they have to start there
>> and then they have to first of all fill
in my blind spots. Mhm. I also just want
to add that I was a really serious
tennis player from the age of nine until
when I dropped out of college and I
discovered rather early on how much more
I love doubles than singles, you know,
because it was fun and it was social and
it was somebody could if I didn't have a
good forehand volley and Shelley Adams
did, then I had I could do the things
that I could do so well. I had a great
backhand down the line shot and I do to
this day. But um
>> Annie protects me from myself when she
reads my stuff
>> and it's just so much more fun.
>> Is it fair to say that this book Good
Writing Talking about collaboration is
your love child together? Is it fair to
say that?
>> Kind of.
>> Yeah.
>> I I've been talking with Annie Lamont
and Neil Allen. You say to question
cliches and to twist them. So maybe we
can twist the love child cliche in some
way. You can both help.
>> You did.
>> Yeah.
>> They have written a new book
together. It's called Good Writing. 36
Ways to Improve Your Sentences
and all kinds of other things about
writing towards the really really. Can I
throw in as many reallyies as I want
here? and notice at the end because it's
my gosh darn podcast and who knows how
they'll edit it. Writing towards the
really really really real. Thank you
both so much. Good writing.
>> Thank you Tammy.
>> Thank you.
>> And we really really do love you as a
cousin and we love the sounds true
community most of all. So thank you so
much for having us.
>> Thank you both. Good writing friends.
Thank you Tammy.
Yeah.